<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" ?>
<!-- This is a WordPress eXtended RSS file generated by WordPress as an export of your site. -->
<!-- It contains information about your site's posts, pages, comments, categories, and other content. -->
<!-- You may use this file to transfer that content from one site to another. -->
<!-- This file is not intended to serve as a complete backup of your site. -->

<!-- To import this information into a WordPress site follow these steps: -->
<!-- 1. Log in to that site as an administrator. -->
<!-- 2. Go to Tools: Import in the WordPress admin panel. -->
<!-- 3. Install the "WordPress" importer from the list. -->
<!-- 4. Activate & Run Importer. -->
<!-- 5. Upload this file using the form provided on that page. -->
<!-- 6. You will first be asked to map the authors in this export file to users -->
<!--    on the site. For each author, you may choose to map to an -->
<!--    existing user on the site or to create a new user. -->
<!-- 7. WordPress will then import each of the posts, pages, comments, categories, etc. -->
<!--    contained in this file into your site. -->

	<!-- generator="WordPress/5.4.1" created="2020-05-23 21:52" -->
<rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:excerpt="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/excerpt/"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:wp="http://wordpress.org/export/1.2/"
>

<channel>
	<title>JURIST - Commentary - Legal News &#38; Commentary</title>
	<link>https://www.jurist.org/commentary</link>
	<description>EXPERT ANALYSIS OF GLOBAL LEGAL DEVELOPMENTS.</description>
	<pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 21:52:23 +0000</pubDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<wp:wxr_version>1.2</wp:wxr_version>
	<wp:base_site_url>http://www.jurist.org/</wp:base_site_url>
	<wp:base_blog_url>https://www.jurist.org/commentary</wp:base_blog_url>

		<wp:author><wp:author_id>8</wp:author_id><wp:author_login><![CDATA[jdl]]></wp:author_login><wp:author_email><![CDATA[jeremiah.lee@gmail.com]]></wp:author_email><wp:author_display_name><![CDATA[Jeremiah Lee]]></wp:author_display_name><wp:author_first_name><![CDATA[]]></wp:author_first_name><wp:author_last_name><![CDATA[]]></wp:author_last_name></wp:author>

				
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=5.4.1</generator>

		<item>
		<title>&#034;Faithless Electors&#034;: The Wild Card</title>
		<link>https://www.jurist.org/commentary/2000/12/ross-faithless-electors/</link>
		<pubDate>Sat, 09 Dec 2000 21:21:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jdl]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jurist.org/forum/2000/12/ross-faithless-electors.php</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In past elections, so-called "faithless electors" cast innocuously eccentric votes that provided a quaint reminder of one of the archaic curiosities of the presidential selection process. After providing a rare element of surprise in the otherwise perfunctory Electoral College ritual, these independent spirits who voted for someone other than their party's nominee would vanish from the national spotlight, to be immortalized only in obscure historical footnotes.</p>

<p>This year, however, faithless electors could change the outcome of the election.</p>

<p>If George W. Bush wins Florida's 25 electoral votes, he will have only a three vote lead over Al Gore - 271 to 268. If only two electors defected from Bush, the vote would tie and the election would be decided by the House of Representatives. If Bush lost three votes, Gore would win if none of Gore's own electors defected.</p>

<p>Various politicians and scholars dismiss these prospects as preposterous. They point out that faithless electors have cast only nine of the 21, 291 electoral votes recorded since 1796. No elector has defected since 1988, and two defections never have occurred in a single election.</p>

<p>Moreover, no faithless elector since 1796 has voted for the candidate of the major opposing party. Persons who scornfully dismiss the prospect of defections this year also emphasize that most electors are devout party loyalists who hold public office, perform yeoman service in the party trenches, or donate generously to the party purse. Electors often are selected precisely because of their political reliability, and an elector's failure to vote for her party's candidate normally would destroy the party career that she so diligently has labored to build.</p>

<p>In an election that has thus far confounded all expectations, however, additional bizarre occurrences should surprise no one.</p>

<p>For the first time since the disputed election of 1876, there is at least a modest possibility of decisive defections by electors. During recent weeks, two Republican electors in Florida and one in Arizona have made provocative remarks about their independence. Moreover, several other Republican electors polled by the <em>Wall Street Journal</em> coyly declined to declare without equivocation that they will vote for Bush. Meanwhile, one Democratic elector in the District of Columbia has threatened to withhold her vote for Gore to protest the federal government's treatment of the District.</p>

<p>Although some observers contend that electoral defections are particularly unlikely this year since they could actually affect the election's outcome, the closeness of the election might actually encourage defections. As Lawrence D. Longley, an Electoral College expert, predicted at a 1992 congressional hearing, "faithless electors...would likely proliferate in the instance of an election producing a very close electoral vote count." Although defection in a close contest naturally would aggravate the obloquy they would suffer within their own party, some electors might succumb to the lure of celebrity. There is also a danger that some would hope or expect to receive favors from the opposing party, although there is presently no evidence that any unsavory deals are being made. In a recent letter to the Washington Times, a Bush elector from Texas warned that many electors may be "in financial straits" and that "[c]asting a vote for the 'will of the people' may sound more convincing if it also is in one's economic self-interest."</p>

<p>There is no doubt that some persons are encouraging Bush electors to defect to Gore.</p>

<p>Many Republican electors report that they are receiving numerous communications from strangers who urge them to vote for Gore. A Web site operated by two Claremont-McKenna students has posted names of Bush electors whose states require no pledge of loyalty and is asking its visitors to urge these electors to vote for Gore because the election of a candidate who failed to win the popular vote would create a "serious legitimacy crisis."</p>

<p>Encouragement of electors to change their votes is not a new idea. Democrats appear to have made a similar appeal to some Republicans after the election of 1876, when the shift of one electoral vote would have elected Samuel Tilden, who had received more votes than his Republican opponent, Rutherford B. Hayes. In 1977, Robert Dole revealed that Republicans had considered trying to woo Democratic electors during the brief period after the 1976 election when Ohio's electoral votes remained in the balance since a shift of five electoral votes would have thrown the election to Gerald R. Ford if Ohio had gone Republican.</p>

<p>The mischief that such efforts could engender has led even some advocates of retention of the Electoral College to advocate a constitutional amendment to eliminate human electors and provide for an automatic tally of electoral vote. Judith A. Best, a leading authority on the Electoral College, is among the advocates of this procedure.</p>

<p>On November 21, Gore publicly disavowed any effort to encourage electors to change their vote and he declared that he would not accept such votes. Early in December, a spokesman for Gore reiterated Gore's disapproval of attempts to sway electors, but indicated that Gore might lack any legal means to reject the votes of defectors.</p>

<p>While there probably is no way that Gore could actually reject faithless electoral votes, he might be able to persuade Congress to undertake the constitutionally questionable act of rejecting them. Gore also could enable Bush to become president pursuant to the 25th Amendment: after his inauguration, Gore could arrange for Lieberman's resignation and then appoint Bush vice president (with the consent of Congress) and then resign as president. Of course, this is a most unlikely possibility.</p>

<p>Like so many other aspects of this unprecedented election, the legal implications of faithless voting are muddled, with a maze of disparate authorities pointing in different directions.</p>

<p>The Framers of the Constitution appear to have expected electors to vote freely, since they did not envision political parties or a universal franchise. As Neal R. Peirce and Lawrence D. Longley have pointed out, the Framers intended that the Electoral College would act primarily as a nominating mechanism, with the final decision normally made by the House of Representatives.</p>

<p>With the rapid development of a party system during the early years of the Republic, electors quickly became the instruments of their parties. Custom firmly established that electors would vote for their party's candidates. Generations of electors have therefore tacitly echoed the refrain of Sir Joseph Porter in Gilbert and Sullivan's H.M.S. Pinafore: "I always voted at my party's call and I never thought of thinking for myself at all."</p>

<p>Only two electors defected from their party in the Republic's first century and a half: a Federalist deserted John Adams to vote for Thomas Jefferson in 1796, and a faithless elector in 1820 introduced a chord of 'bad feeling' into the non-partisan "Era of Good Feelings" by denying James Monroe a unanimous re-election.</p>

<p>Although the remaining seven faithless electors have defected from their candidate during the past half-century (in 1948, 1956, 1960, 1968, 1972, 1976, and 1988) , this hardly can be said to have broken the tradition of party fealty. Six of the seven have been conservatives who have voted for a conservative alternative to their own party's candidate rather than for the opposing party's candidate, and the seventh voted for her party's vice presidential nominee (Lloyd Bentsen) in preference to its presidential nominee (Michael Dukakis). As recently as 1996, one South Carolina elector considered voting for conservative Republican Pat Robertson rather than for Republican nominee Robert Dole but remained faithful to Dole after he was advised that his defection would be illegal under South Carolina law.</p>

<p>It is therefore possible that some conservative Bush electors might vote for someone other than Gore to dramatize their disenchantment with mainstream Republicanism, although this is highly unlikely in a close election. It is also possible, as CNN commentator Jeff Greenfield recently pointed out, that conservative Bush electors might threaten to withhold their vote in order to try to extract concessions from Bush.</p>

<p>Approximately half the states and the District of Columbia have enacted statutes that require electors to pledge themselves to vote for their party's nominee. These statutes take various different forms. Only a few impose any penalty for violation, and these penalties generally are light. No faithless elector ever has been prosecuted under one of these statutes.</p>

<p>State supreme court decisions in Kansas in 1896 and in Ohio in 1948 held that electors were free to vote for whomever they chose, at least in the absence of a statute binding them to a candidate. As the Supreme Court of Ohio declared in its opinion in <em>State v. Hummel</em>, "[i]t is only by force of a moral obligation, not a legal one, that the presidential electors pledged to certain candidates fulfill their pledges after election." In 1948, the Supreme Court of Alabama stated in an advisory opinion that electors could vote freely even though a statute required them to support their party's candidate.</p>

<p>A New York trial court in 1933 reached the opposite conclusion in Thomas v. Cohen, a decision holding that names of electors do not need to appear on the ballot because an elector has "a sacred and compelling" obligation to vote for his party's nominee. The court explained that the original discretion of electors had "ripened into a bounden duty." The New York court indicated in dictum that a writ of <em>mandamus </em>could issue to require an elector "to carry out the mandate of the voters of his state."</p>

<p>In 1952, the U.S. Supreme Court in Ray v. Blair, a five to two decision, held that the U.S. Constitution does not prevent a political party from requiring elector candidates in its primary to pledge support for its presidential and vice presidential nominees. Accordingly, the Court reversed a writ of mandamus requiring Alabama's Democratic Party from certifying an elector candidate who refused to sign the pledge. The Court reasoned that the Party was free to require a pledge in the absence of any language in Article II of the Constitution or the Twelfth Amendment that would forbid such a pledge. Moreover, the Court referred to the long tradition of electors supporting their party's nominee. The Court also pointed out that the pledge was only a condition of candidacy in the primary, although the Court hinted that it would reach the same conclusion even if the restraint were imposed upon electors after their selection. The Court did not address the question of sanctions for violation of the pledge.</p>

<p>A dissenting opinion of Justice Robert H. Jackson, joined by William O. Douglas, argued that the language and history of Article II and the Twelfth Amendment contemplate "that electors would be free agents, to exercise an independent and nonpartisan judgment." Although Jackson acknowledged that electors had become "voluntary party lackeys and intellectual nonentities" and that "the Electoral College suffered atrophy almost indistinguishable from rigor mortis," he denied that "powers or discretions granted to federal officials by the Federal Constitution can be forfeited by the Court for disuse."</p>

<p>Even if electors may vote freely, with or without state restrictions, there is the possibility that Congress might reject the vote of any elector who failed to support her party's nominee, particularly if the elector had formally pledged such support pursuant to state law. A federal statute, the Electoral Count Act of 1887 (the same statute that was at issue in part in the recent U.S. Supreme Court litigation), provides that Congress must count those votes that it determines to have been "regularly given." The meaning of this language is not clear. As Professor Michael J. Glennon of the University of California at Davis School of Law recently observed, these words "could turn out to be the shibboleth of 2001, much as 'impeachable offence' was in 1999. The phrase is undefined."</p>

<p>Congress has considered the meaning of this phrase only once, in January 1969, when it debated about whether to accept the vote of Dr. Lloyd W. Bailey, a North Carolina Republican elector who voted for American Independent candidate George C. Wallace rather than Republican Richard M. Nixon, who had carried North Carolina. Senators who favored rejection of Bailey's ballot argued that faithless electors deprive voters of due process and equal protection in violation of the Fourteenth Amendment. After extended deliberations, Congress accepted Bailey's ballot by a margin of 58 to 33 in the Senate and 228 to 170 in the House. Although the vote did not follow party lines, conservatives tended to favor electoral independence, while liberals generally opposed it. Many of the senators who voted to count Bailey's vote emphasized that they nevertheless favored reform or abolition of the Electoral College. Al Gore's father, Albert Gore, Sr., voted to accept Bailey's ballot, and he declared during the debate that "the presidential elector duly chosen is an independent agent."</p>

<p>The votes of the eight other faithless electors have not precipitated congressional challenges, although none of these electors came from states that prohibited electors from voting for someone other than her party's candidate. The only time that Congress has refused to count electors' votes was in 1872, when it rejected three electoral votes for Horace Greeley, the Democratic candidate, who had died shortly after the election.</p>

<p>In a detailed analysis of the legislative history and language of the Act published four years ago, Beverly J. Ross and William Josephson concluded that Congress's decision to count Dr. Bailey's vote "was constitutionally appropriate" because Article II expressly permits each state to appoint electors in such Manner as its legislature may direct. Although Article II permits Congress to count electoral votes and to select the time of electors appointment and the date on which they vote, Ross and Josephson concluded that "[t]hese powers are hardly mandates for Congress to impose a federal binding requirement under the Electoral Count Act."</p>

<p>When, however, a state (unlike North Carolina in 1968) has a law prohibiting defection by electors, Congress or a court could much more easily interpret the phrase "regularly given" to permit Congress to reject the vote of a faithless elector. Ronald D. Rotunda has explained that Congress also might have concurrent jurisdiction to enforce these state laws insofar as congressional action merely would require "the elector to keep his campaign pledge, thus preventing what, in some cases, could otherwise be a fraud on the voters."</p>

<p>As Bruce Fein recently pointed out, Congress could retroactively amend the Electoral Count Act to prohibit electors from defecting from their party's candidate. Retroactive application of the Act would be ironic, however, since the statute was intended in part to prevent states from changing the rules for election procedure after an election. Although such a statute might be constitutional, particularly under the Fourteenth Amendment, its enactment might unduly intrude upon the powers of those states that do not bind electors.</p>

<p>In the face of legal ambiguities about whether an elector may defect from her party's candidate, each elector must search her own conscience in determining whether to switch her vote. Although electors in the states that bind electors to their party's candidate might regard themselves as legally bound to vote for Bush despite ambiguities about the constitutionality of such legislation, the 172 Bush electors in the eighteen states carried by Bush that do not prohibit defection by electors are particularly free to base their decision upon their own concepts of morality and justice.</p>

<p>For most electors, the decision is inevitable. Party loyalty and partisan sympathies firmly bind most electors to their party's candidate.</p>

<p>Moreover, most electors appear to believe that personal honor requires fidelity to their pledge to support their party's nominee. Even many electors whose states do not explicitly bind their vote believe that they would break faith with both the party that nominated them and the voters who elected them if they frustrated the wishes and expectations of that party and those voters. When Democrats urged the poet James Russell Lowell of Massachusetts to switch his electoral vote from Hayes to Tilden in 1876, Lowell explained his refusal by declaring that "it is a plain question of trust." During recent weeks, many of today's Republican electors have echoed this sentiment..</p>

<p>If Bush wins Florida's electoral votes some Bush electors nevertheless may be responsive to the argument that justice requires Gore's election because Gore appears to have won more popular votes. Doubts about the propriety or legality of Bush's victory in Florida also might influence some electors that Gore has a moral claim to the presidency. Some G.O.P. electors also might conclude that Bush's election would be inimical to long-term Republican and national interests since Democratic rancor over the election would greatly diminish Bush's ability to effectively govern.</p>

<p>On the other hand, Gore's failure to receive an absolute majority of the vote may diminish any moral claim in favor of his election. Moreover, the closeness of the popular vote - less than one-third of one percent of the vote - may weaken any argument that Bush's election clearly would frustrate the popular will. Since both Republicans and Democrats have alleged voting irregularities, some Republican electors may share the perception, not uncommon among Republicans, that Bush actually won the popular vote.</p>

<p>Any Bush elector who believes that Gore has a moral claim to the presidency or that Bush's claim to the presidency is so clouded that his election would be adverse to Republican or national interests might therefore conclude that he could vote for Gore without breaking faith with his party or with the voters since neither anticipated the amazing turn of events since the election. This position would be difficult to maintain, however, if the Republican Party did not countenance vote-switching. Moreover, public opinion polls indicate that the vast majority of Bush voters still believe that Bush should receive the presidency.</p>

<p>Defecting electors also might claim that they were placing the national interest above the interest of their party. As Dr. Bailey declared in a public letter explaining his defection from Nixon in 1968, "it is my duty to place loyalty to my country before loyalty to my political party." Similarly, the novelist James A. Michener, a 1968 Democratic elector in Pennsylvania, contended that the national interest justified his vow before the election to vote for someone other than Democratic nominee Hubert Humphrey if no candidate received an Electoral College majority and if such defection were necessary to prevent "chicanery" in the House of Representatives.</p>

<p>Even if no defections occur this year, the widespread speculation about the prospect of faithless electors in the context of a close election has called sharp attention to yet another anomaly in the presidential selection process. The "faithless elector" problem almost certainly will be among the multitude of issues that will receive careful consideration by Congress and citizens during the months following the outcome of the election.</p>

<p><em><br />
William G. Ross teaches Constitutional Law and Constitutional History at Cumberland School of Law, Samford University, Birmingham, Alabama. He is a 1979 graduate of Harvard Law School.<br />
</em></p>

<p><strong>Suggested Citation</strong>: William G. Ross, Faithless Electors: The Wild Card, JURIST - Academic Commentary, Dec. 9, 2000, https://www.jurist.org/forum/2000/12/ross-faithless-electors.php.</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[In past elections, so-called &quot;faithless electors&quot; cast innocuously eccentric votes that provided a quaint reminder of one of the archaic curiosities of the presidential selection process. After providing a rare element of surprise in the otherwise perfunctory Electoral College ritual,...]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>80159</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2000-12-09 16:21:11]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2000-12-09 21:21:11]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[ross-faithless-electors]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="post_tag" nicename="affiliation-samford-university-school-of-law"><![CDATA[affiliation: Samford University School of Law]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="author-william-g-ross"><![CDATA[author: William G. Ross]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jurist_previous_post_status]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_pods_commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
					<item>
		<title>Why Not Split the Presidential Term?</title>
		<link>https://www.jurist.org/commentary/2000/11/why-not-split-the-presidential-term/</link>
		<pubDate>Fri, 17 Nov 2000 18:40:08 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jdl]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jurist.org/forum/2000/11/why-not-split-the-presidential-term.php</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>It should be obvious to everyone by now that no one ever will know which presidential candidate actually won more popular votes, either in Florida or nationwide. The Florida recount process can never yield an accurate result, for efforts to divine the meaning of the notorious chads are hopelessly compromised by the certainty of ambiguity and the possibility of accident, mistake, and fraud. Similarly, the national count is so riddled with mistakes and allegations of fraud by both sides that it is impossible to say with certainty that Gore won a plurality, even though this may appear more likely than not.</p>

<p>Since voting technology is too primitive to produce a decisive victor, the courts now seem likely to determine the winner. The law, however, is no less unencumbered with ambiguity than are the chads. Rarely have we seen a more perfect example of how different interpretations of the law, each perfectly reasonable on its own terms, can yield opposite results. It is therefore hardly surprising that legal interpretations, even among the general public, are almost perfectly correlated with partisan sympathies. In the absence of any real legal compass, one can hardly blame any judge for permitting party loyalties to determine the outcome of his or her decision.</p>

<p>The result of any judicial determination of the election is likely to be tragic. The winner, degraded by tawdry legal battles and lacking legitimacy in the opinion of half the nation, will have difficulty governing. Embittered supporters of the losing candidate will question the integrity of the political process. The courts will lose prestige, for the sophistry of their rulings will be naked for all to see.</p>

<p>There is, however, a dignified way out of this morass, one that could immediately circumvent all the sophistry about chads and the Florida election manual and would moot speculation about voting fraud or mistake. The candidates could simply agree that each would serve for two years.</p>

<p>The constitutional procedure for such a compromise is clearly permitted by the 25th Amendment. After the candidates decided which man would serve first, the one who would serve later would instruct a sufficient number of his electors to vote for the opposing presidential and vice presidential nominees. Since half of the states permit electors to vote for anyone of their choice, the candidate should not have any difficulty finding a sufficient number of faithful "faithless" electors. The vice president who served the first half of the term would resign after two years, the president would nominate his erstwhile opponent to become vice president, both houses of Congress would confirm the nomination, and the president would then resign.</p>

<p>The prospect of a president resigning in favor of his electoral opponent is not completely unprecedented. In 1916, Woodrow Wilson intended to resign from office if he lost the election to Charles Evans Hughes in order to prevent the nation from suffering from a four-month hiatus of power at a time when the nation needed firm leadership in the face of a growing threat of war. Wilson would have requested the resignation of his vice president and then resigned after appointing Hughes to the office of secretary of state, which by statute at that time would have placed him first in the line of succession.</p>

<p>Although there probably would be no legal way to force the president to resign after two years, public opinion almost certainly would dictate that he honor his promise, especially since the entire nation would have witnessed this pledge. While there likewise would be no legal way to require members of Congress to confirm the nomination of the other candidate to the office of vice president, the two candidates could at least extract informal pledges from members of Congress to cooperate with their compromise. Again, public opinion would almost surely require fidelity to the promises. In order to minimize the likelihood of opposition by persons who are not yet members of Congress, the candidates might arrange for the confirmation of the new vice president in advance of January 3, 2003, when the Congress elected in 2002 will assemble.</p>

<p>The principal practical problem with this arrangement would involve the question of which candidate would serve first. Both probably would prefer to be second insofar as the second president would enjoy the advantage of incumbency in the 2004 election and would enjoy the prospect of as long as ten uninterrupted years in office. On the other hand, the candidate who took office first could perhaps find political advantage in assuming office at a time of deep national division since this would afford the opportunity to play a Gerald Ford-like role of national healer that would nicely position him for a return to the White House after 2004. There might also be some special reason why one candidate might prefer to serve first; perhaps, for example, one would be willing to gamble that the economy would be worse after 2002 or that significant Supreme Court resignations are likely during the next two years.</p>

<p>If the candidates could not agree about who would serve first, perhaps they could arbitrarily settle the question by a sophisticated version of a coin toss. Or, why not an actual coin toss? When two coalitions of parties won equal numbers of parliamentary seats in a Swedish general election a number of years ago, the two sides tossed a coin to determine which side would form a government. If this process resolved a crisis in Sweden, one of the world's richest and most politically stable nations, it ought to be good enough for the United States. Although some might say that a coin toss would demean the integrity of the presidential election process and mock democracy, it could hardly be more farcical than the process of selecting a president by haggling about flapping chads and the intricacies of Palm Beach County election procedure.</p>

<p>Of course, a split term would have the obvious disadvantage of placing a virtual lame duck into office for the first two years. The first president could not expect to accomplish much legislatively since he would be destined to serve only for two years. But no president is likely to advance any significant legislative program during the coming two years anyway, because Congress is so deeply divided. And at least this president's legislative program would not be hamstrung by the intense partisan rancor that is likely to haunt anyone who emerges from a protracted legal struggle. The first president also would likely have difficulty in appointing lower federal judges since the opposition party in the Senate could easily kill many nominations by delay, knowing that the new president would probably not re-nominate them during the next session of Congress. Again, however, a crippled president could face even worse opposition in the Senate over any type of nomination.</p>

<p>At first glance, this proposal for compromise seems far-fetched, perhaps even surreal. It is less bizarre, however, than the spectacle of an election in which only protracted litigation resulting in murky judicial opinions interpreting a few hundred hopelessly ambiguous ballots and conflicting laws will prevent the ascension of Strom Thurmond to the presidency if the Speaker of the House, Dennis Hastert, refused to serve. An amicable division of the presidential term would also help to diminish partisan tensions and promote public confidence in the stability, rationality, and maturity of the nation's leaders.</p>

<p><em><br />
William G. Ross teaches Constitutional Law and Constitutional History at Cumberland School of Law, Samford University, Birmingham, Alabama. He is a 1979 graduate of Harvard Law School.<br />
</em></p>

<p><strong>Suggested Citation</strong>: William G. Ross, Why Not Split the Presidential Term?, JURIST - Academic Commentary, Nov. 17, 2000, https://www.jurist.org/forum/2016/04/why-not-split-the-presidential-term.php.</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[It should be obvious to everyone by now that no one ever will know which presidential candidate actually won more popular votes, either in Florida or nationwide. The Florida recount process can never yield an accurate result, for efforts to...]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>80202</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2000-11-17 13:40:08]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2000-11-17 18:40:08]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[why-not-split-the-presidential-term]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="post_tag" nicename="affiliation-samford-university-school-of-law"><![CDATA[affiliation: Samford University School of Law]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="author-william-g-ross"><![CDATA[author: William G. Ross]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jurist_previous_post_status]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_pods_commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
					<item>
		<title>Does the Supreme Court Rush in Where Wise Judges Would Fear to Tread?</title>
		<link>https://www.jurist.org/commentary/2000/11/does-the-supreme-court-rush-in-where-wise-judges-would-fear-to-tread/</link>
		<pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2000 18:45:30 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jdl]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jurist.org/forum/2000/11/does-the-supreme-court-rush-in-where-wise-judges-would-fear-to-tread.php</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The U.S. Supreme Court's intervention in the disputed presidential election was virtually inevitable, despite wishful predictions by Democrats that the Court would not meddle with state election law. As countless commentators have pointed out, the electoral impasse provides yet another illustration of the wisdom of Alexis de Tocqueville's overworked observation that "scarcely any political question arises in the United States that is not resolved, sooner or later, into a judicial question." A corollary to this truism is that any major judicial question eventually finds its way to the Supreme Court. As has happened so often in American history, the Court may attempt to answer questions that the political process has failed to resolve.</p>

<p>In particular, the Court is expected to address the constitutionality of the Florida Supreme Court's decision requiring the Florida Secretary of State to extend by eleven days the deadline for accepting county certificates reflecting manual recounts of votes. The Court will consider whether the Florida court's decision violated Article II of the Constitution, which gives power to a state's legislature to determine the manner of appointing presidential electors. The Court will also consider whether the Florida decision violated the due process rights of voters by contravening a federal statute, Title 3 Section 5 of the United States Code, which requires states to resolve any disputes over the appointment of presidential electors by exclusive reference to state law enacted before election day; attorneys for Bush contend that the Florida court's decision violated the statute by changing the law after the election. The Court has also asked the parties to brief and argue the question of what consequences would follow from the Court's finding that the Florida decision failed to comply with the federal statute.</p>

<p>Attorneys for Bush argued in their brief in favor of certiorari that the Court properly has jurisdiction because "the federal Constitution and congressional enactments make clear that state laws regarding the appointment of presidential electors are a matter of federal concern." In opposing certiorari, Gore's attorneys argued that the Court's intervention would improperly intrude upon a question that "is fundamental to state sovereignty."</p>

<p>Regardless of the merits of the lawsuit or the question of whether the Court has jurisdiction in this case, one might properly question whether the Court is the proper or ideal agency for resolving the election controversy and whether its resolution by the Court would serve the best interests of either political party, the Court, or the nation as a whole.</p>

<p>In their brief in support of certiorari, Bush's attorneys suggested that the Court's involvement would help to prevent "the ascension of a President of questionable legitimacy." In response, Gore's attorneys argued that the Court's interference with state law "would only diminish the legitimacy of the outcome of the election."</p>

<p>While Bush's attorneys are probably correct that the Court's intervention could help to legitimize the election of the next President (if the election in any way depends upon the Court's ruling), the Court's intervention might diminish the legitimacy of the Court. Although this diminution would probably be slight, any diminution would be unfortunate. At the very least, some of the inevitable partisan rancor about the election may find expression in hostility toward the Court.</p>

<p>The Court's intervention could go far toward legitimizing the election of the next President insofar as the Court commands more public respect than any other political institution. In particular, the High Court's review of the Supreme Court of Florida's decision could erase the bitterness among Bush supporters caused by their widespread perception - however unwarranted - that the Florida court's unanimous decision was influenced by the fact that all seven jurists are Democrats. The Supreme Court justices, in contrast to the Florida judges, do not wear their partisan labels on the exterior of their robes and they do not need to face the electorate in retention elections. Even if the Supreme Court affirmed the Florida decision, Republicans would be hard-pressed to allege hopeless bias by a Court in which seven of the nine justices are at least nominal Republicans who were nominated by Republican presidents.</p>

<p>Although each justice was identified with a political party before his or her appointment to the Court, and each was nominated by a president of his or her own party, the justices are not known for having strong party ties. With the exception of Chief Justice Rehnquist and Justice O'Connor, none of the justices was deeply involved in partisan politics before his or her appointment. Only O'Connor, who served Republican majority leader of the Arizona Senate, has held significant partisan elective office. By historical standards, the present Court is politically virginal. The Court in past times often was a second career for superannuated governors and senators. A former president (William Howard Taft), a former presidential nominee (Charles Evans Hughes), and former vice presidential nominee (Earl Warren), all Republicans, have served as Chief Justice. And, in contrast to today's Nine, numerous justices of yesteryear harbored presidential ambitions, sometimes quite openly, while others acted as informal presidential advisors.</p>

<p>But while few if any of the present Justices have fierce party loyalties or engage in partisan activities, each of the Justices is known to adhere broadly to a political and ideological position that tends to match those of one of the political parties. While these positions generally correlate with their nominal party affiliation, at least two of the "Republican" Justices &mdash; Stevens and Souter &mdash; have voting patterns that broadly favor Democratic positions on issues.</p>

<p>Even if the Justices strive mightily to exclude political considerations from their deliberation of the election case, votes that seem to correlate with partisan sympathies might actually exacerbate partisan tensions in the nation. If, for example, the Court divided five-to-four in favor of the Republicans, with Rehnquist, O'Connor, Kennedy, Scalia, and Thomas in the majority and Stevens, Souter, Ginsberg and Breyer in dissent, the public might well wonder whether partisan sympathies affected the outcome. Such suspicions might be particularly pronounced since such a result would be opposite to the Court's usual alignment on issues involving federalism. The objectivity of the Justices in such a situation would be particularly subject to doubt insofar as the likelihood of vacancies on the Court during the next few years gives the Justices an especially strong reason to care about who becomes the next president. Indeed, some of the Justices may have a very personal interest in the outcome insofar as it may affect the timing of their retirements.</p>

<p>Of course, suspicions of partisanship could hardly develop if the votes of the Justices are correlated with their positions on federalism. If this happened, Justices who usually vote in favor of the states' rights positions favored by Republicans would vote in favor of the Democrats while the Justices who tend to favor broad federal power would vote for the Republican position. Similarly, the Court could ameliorate suspicions of partisanship if its vote were unanimous or at least not closely divided.</p>

<p>Even if the Court could escape charges of partisanship, however, the Coury's involvement in such a highly partisan issue could undermine public respect for the Court. The Court would still have ventured into what Felix Frankfurter disapprovingly called a "political thicket." Unless the Court can conceive of some solomonic solution, its decision potentially will antagonize half the nation. Although the Court has often offended broad segments of the nation by ruling on highly divisive political issues &mdash; school segregation, school prayer and reapportionment are the classic examples from the past half century &mdash; even the Court's most controversial rulings have usually commanded the support of most political leaders and at least a majority of the general public.</p>

<p>On the rare occasions when the Court has ventured to rule on issues on which there is not at least a broad national consensus, the Court's prestige has suffered. The Court's 1857 Dred Scott decision on slavery remains the classic example of what Charles Evans Hughes called a "self-inflicted wound." And the Court's hostility toward highly popular New Deal legislation during the 1930s precipitated Franklin Roosevelt's attempt to pack the Court, which failed only after the Court changed its direction.	In more recent times, the Court wisely sidestepped opportunities to rule on the legality of the Vietnam War.</p>

<p>Until now, the only significant occasion in which the Court was at the center of a controversy involving the fate of a presidency was in July 1974, when the Court by an eight to zero vote required Richard Nixon to comply with a subpoena to turn potentially incriminating tapes over to the Watergate special prosecutor. Although the Court's decision sealed the doom of the Nixon presidency, the Court's constitutional position was arguably stronger in that case because the question of whether Nixon had to comply with a subpoena issued by a federal district court was unequivocally federal and clearly judicial. Moreover, the Court's practical political position was stronger than it is now because there was a widespread consensus by the summer of 1974 that Nixon should leave office. Indeed, Republicans generally may have been even more pleased by the Court's decision than were Democrats insofar as the decision helped to ease the removal of a president who had become an embarrassment to his party.</p>

<p>Even if the Court rules on the merits and does not damage its own prestige in making its decision, the procedural issues before the Court still will fail to settle the question of how to determine, to the most reasonable possible extent, which candidate received more votes. The Court's decision about the deadline for certifying votes likewise will not necessarily resolve issues about the validity of the votes certified and therefore will not necessarily foreclose additional litigation.</p>

<p>In some ways, of course, the confinement of the Court's adjudication to a procedural issue may protect the Court's reputation, since the Justices -- at least in the present case --will not be placed in the awkward position of actually deciding who won the election, a posture that could result in one swing Justice picking the next President.</p>

<p>Since the Court's decision will involve only one discrete subject rather than any on-going controversy, the Court's decision is not likely to precipitate any movement to curb the Court's powers. Even if such a movement began, the Court would probably survive any attacks with all of its powers intact, just as it has during so many other times of controversy. By spending some of its precious goodwill, however, the Court might have less public support from which to draw in future years as it adjudicates controversial issues that more clearly lie within its jurisdiction.</p>

<p>The paradox of the Court's power is that the Court is potent because it uses its power sparingly. We should hope that the Justices considered this before granting certiorari in the Bush case.</p>

<p><em><br />
William G. Ross teaches Constitutional Law and Constitutional History at Cumberland School of Law, Samford University, Birmingham, Alabama. He is a 1979 graduate of Harvard Law School.<br />
</em></p>

<p><strong>Suggested Citation</strong>: William G. Ross, Does the Supreme Court Rush in Where Wise Judges Would Fear to Tread?, JURIST - Academic Commentary, Nov. 26, 2000, https://www.jurist.org/forum/2000/11/does-the-supreme-court-rush-in-where-wise-judges-would-fear-to-tread.php.</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The U.S. Supreme Court&apos;s intervention in the disputed presidential election was virtually inevitable, despite wishful predictions by Democrats that the Court would not meddle with state election law. As countless commentators have pointed out, the electoral impasse provides yet another...]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>80203</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2000-11-26 13:45:30]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2000-11-26 18:45:30]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[does-the-supreme-court-rush-in-where-wise-judges-would-fear-to-tread]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="post_tag" nicename="affiliation-samford-university-school-of-law"><![CDATA[affiliation: Samford University School of Law]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="author-william-g-ross"><![CDATA[author: William G. Ross]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jurist_previous_post_status]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_pods_commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
					<item>
		<title>Don&amp;apos;t Litigate - Negotiate!</title>
		<link>https://www.jurist.org/commentary/2000/11/dont-litigate-negotiate/</link>
		<pubDate>Tue, 28 Nov 2000 18:53:20 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jdl]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jurist.org/forum/2000/11/dont-litigate-negotiate.php</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The dispute over the election has developed into a constitutional crisis. With George W. Bush claiming victory and Al Gore refusing to concede, the election's outcome now seems destined to depend on judicial determination of complex and perhaps novel constitutional issues.</p>

<p>Rather than attempting to resolve the actual vote count in the most equitable way possible, the Supreme Court litigation &mdash; and many of the numerous cases pending in other courts &mdash; is not calculated to produce a comprehensive and accurate count of the votes. Instead, this litigation constitutes the legal equivalent of musical chairs, in which one party may win by a technicality when the music of court proceedings finally stops.</p>

<p>Litigation will impose heavy costs on both parties. Regardless of how the litigation ends, the victor is likely to govern over a deeply fractured nation. Moreover, litigation that results in an award of Florida's electoral votes to Gore would encourage the Republican majority in the Florida legislature or the U.S. Senate to substitute its own judgment for that of the Florida voters. While it might be constitutional for the legislature to select its own slate of electors or for the Senate to refuse to recognize Gore electors from Florida, either action would certainly exacerbate partisan tensions and contribute to a perception that the election was "stolen."</p>

<p>A number of legal commentators during recent days have argued that litigation is the only alternative to riots or civil war. They are wrong. There is a practicable, constitutional, and civilized alternative: negotiation between the parties.</p>

<p>Rather than resorting to contentious and hair-splitting litigation or constitutional maneuvers to settle the election, both parties could enhance public confidence in the electoral process by negotiating a mutually agreeable procedure for counting the votes. Although the vote is so close and ballot ambiguities are so numerous that there is no way ever to determine for certain who actually "won," a uniform and statewide recount procedure agreeable to both sides seems more likely to identify the actual winner than is the litigation.</p>

<p>By creating the perception that the final result optimally reflected the actual choice of the largest number of Floridians rather than the technicalities of the legal process, such an agreement would legitimize the election more than litigation is likely to do. Although the rule of law requires that many disputes must necessarily be decided on the basis of technical rules rather than upon their merits &mdash; statutes of limitation are a prime example &mdash; disagreements ideally ought to be decided upon their substantive merits. Certainly a presidential election should be determined, if possible, upon a complete count of votes rather than legal quibbles about how and when a state official can certify votes. Moreover, a procedure negotiated by the candidates themselves would place the procedure for determining the election's outcome in the hands of the persons for whom the electorate voted, rather than in the laps of unelected judges.</p>

<p>Of course, the vote is so close and the counting of ballots is so ambiguous that the outcome could easily hinge on process rather than substance, even if the parties negotiated a procedure for resolving the dispute. Even so, it would be better for the candidates themselves to agree to this process rather than having a court impose a decision that is likely to leave half the voters deeply dissatisfied.</p>

<p>Such an agreement would require a comprehensive recount. This probably would necessitate a state-wide hand recount, with uniform standards for vote-counting replacing the patchwork of local rules that presently govern the counting. The parties would therefore need to compromise on such nettlesome issues as how to count chads. Republicans, for example, might agree to the count of hanging chads while Democrats would stop trying to count dimpled chads. The parties would also need to agree to bi-partisan review of ballots and perhaps could appoint some type of state-wide panel to review ballots that remained contested after review at the county level. The parties likewise could negotiate some type of compromise about the tally of absentee ballots from overseas.</p>

<p>Negotiated rules for determining the procedure for the recount probably would not resolve all controversy about the recount procedure, because some questions would almost inevitably arise during the recount that the parties could not have anticipated at the outset. The parties could either negotiate a resolution of these problems as they arose, or they could agree to the appointment of a bipartisan panel to resolve these issues. Indeed, the parties might wish to appoint a bipartisan panel for the conduct of all negotiations.</p>

<p>There is a precedent for such negotiation in the disputed election of 1876, when the outcome was determined by an Electoral Commission appointed by Congress early in 1877 with the consent of both political parties. Although the Commission limited its work to determining which electors to certify rather than undertaking any recount or reconsideration of popular votes, the Commission provided a means of resolving the dispute without either protracted litigation or the violence that threatened to erupt after the dispute dragged on for months. The Commission was composed of five U.S. senators (three Republican and two Democratic), five members of the House of Representatives (three Democratic and two Republican) and five members of the U.S. Supreme Court (two Republicans and three Democrats, with the fifth member, a Republican, selected by the other four). The Commission's votes on all fifteen disputed electors were eight-to-seven, divided strictly along party lines. Although Democrats were embittered over the apparent partisanship of a procedure that elected Rutherford B. Hayes as president by a margin of one electoral vote even though he had received fewer popular votes than had his Democratic rival, Democrats refrained from legal or military challenges to the outcome of a process to which they had given their consent.</p>

<p>Although the Commission ultimately provided an alternative to litigation, it was formed only after Democrats had won a court challenge to the certification of electoral votes in Florida, whose four votes were just as critical to the election's outcome as the 25 votes of a much more populated Florida are today. Rushing to the courts to solve political disputes is nothing new.</p>

<p>Of course, the present election ultimately also might be settled through some type of congressional intervention. It is unfortunate, however, that the parties virtually began their post-election contests in the courthouses. Although Gore appears to have made at least some effort to communicate with Bush and has offered to waive objections to time-barred recounts in heavily Republican counties where Bush might have gained votes, both candidates appear to have rushed to the courts without making any serious effort to negotiate a procedure for a recount. This haste to litigate is particularly unseemly insofar as the crisis was caused primarily by the extremely close vote rather than by any apparent egregious misconduct by either side.</p>

<p>The lack of interest in negotiation probably reflects the opinion of both parties that they are more likely to win in the courts and that negotiation would require compromises that neither party could make without losing the election. For example, Democrats may be placing some of their hope for winning the election on disqualification of the several thousand votes in Seminole County that Democrats claim were illegally tainted through assistance that Republicans gave to voters; Bush, however, would never agree to count these votes since this would almost certainly cost him the election. Similarly, it might be pointless for Gore to negotiate a compromise that would not count any ballot that contained any form of a chad.</p>

<p>Negotiation, however, is not an inherently impracticable solution. There is no inherent reason why negotiation is more dicey for either party than is litigation. Taking into realistic account the present posture of their respective strengths and weaknesses, the parties could negotiate an agreement that would create no more risk to either than would the present litigation. Naturally, neither party would agree to a compromise procedure that would seem to surrender any advantage they could achieve through the legal system or that would result in its likely defeat. The present vote remains so close that it remains possible to forge a procedure from which both parties would expect to benefit. Although the compromise might contravene some of the prerogatives of local election officials, such officials presumably could probably ratify the compromise by consent. There is no apparent reason why they would wish to withhold such consent to a compromise made by their party leaders in the apparent best interests of their party.</p>

<p>It is very possible that such negotiations would fail to produce a mutually-agreeable procedure for counting the votes and that the parties would still need turn to the courts for determine the outcome. Even if negotiations successfully established such a procedure, it is likewise possible that the procedure would break down under the stress of partisan strife and the parties again would need to go to court. And, even if the process were completed and produced a putative winner, it is quite possible that the losing side would claim that the process was tainted by partisan prejudice and ultimately would try to litigate the outcome. At least, however, they would have tried to reach an agreement for an outcome that would avoid litigation and thereby confer legitimacy on the winner insofar as the winner consented to the rules and procedures by which the outcome was determined.</p>

<p>The decision of the parties to litigate rather than negotiate is symptomatic of the tendency of Americans to look to the courts as their sole refuge for redress of grievances and to litigation as a first course of action rather than as a last resort after other alternatives have failed.</p>

<p>The intransigence of the candidates also is reminiscent of the first presidential debate of 1976, when Gerald Ford and Jimmy Carter stood frozen in silence at their podiums for thirty-eight minutes after the audio system crashed. Just as the candidates then would have enhanced public respect for themselves by talking to one another, the candidates today would prevent a further erosion of public faith in the political system if they were willing to negotiate a procedure for determining a fair vote recount. Both of the candidates during recent days have expressed their desire to "bring the nation together." It is difficult to see how either can bring the nation together if he cannot bring himself together with his opponent to try to negotiate a resolution of this rapidly evolving crisis.</p>

<p><em><br />
William G. Ross teaches Constitutional Law and Constitutional History at Cumberland School of Law, Samford University, Birmingham, Alabama. He is a 1979 graduate of Harvard Law School.<br />
</em></p>

<p><strong>Suggested Citation</strong>: William G. Ross, Don't Litigate - Negotiate!, JURIST - Academic Commentary, Nov. 11, 2000, https://www.jurist.org/forum/2000/11/dont-litigate-negotiate.php.</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The dispute over the election has developed into a constitutional crisis. With George W. Bush claiming victory and Al Gore refusing to concede, the election&apos;s outcome now seems destined to depend on judicial determination of complex and perhaps novel constitutional...]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>80204</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2000-11-28 13:53:20]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2000-11-28 18:53:20]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[dont-litigate-negotiate]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="post_tag" nicename="affiliation-samford-university-school-of-law"><![CDATA[affiliation: Samford University School of Law]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="author-william-g-ross"><![CDATA[author: William G. Ross]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jurist_previous_post_status]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_pods_commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
					<item>
		<title>Election Roulette: The Pistol Finally Fires</title>
		<link>https://www.jurist.org/commentary/2000/12/election-roulette-the-pistol-finally-fires/</link>
		<pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2000 18:58:11 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jdl]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jurist.org/forum/2000/12/election-roulette-the-pistol-finally-fires.php</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>The most complicated bit of governmental machinery which the modern world has to exhibit is that which is employed in the selection of the chief executive officer...for the United States...It is almost marvelous that any people should have preserved political unity for a century under such a loose and decentralized system of election of its chief magistrate. </blockquote>

<p>John W. Burgess, <em>The Law of the Electoral Count</em>, 3 Political Science Quarterly 633 (1888).</p>

<p><br />
Every four years for nearly two centuries, the United States has played the political equivalent of Russian Roulette when it has conducted a presidential election. This year, the gun finally exploded. How much injury it has inflicted on the body politic is not yet clear.</p>

<p>History demonstrates that this year's electoral cliffhanger is not a freak accident but rather is merely the latest in a long series of remarkably close elections which often have ended in doubt and acrimony after considerable conflict. This history, which is briefly reviewed below, indicates that the turmoil over the present election was predictable and that a similar mess will almost surely occur again if the present system is not reformed.</p>

<p>Although the House of Representative's selection of a president in 1824, the disputed election of 1876, and the close and questionable Kennedy-Nixon contest of 1960 have received much attention in recent weeks as news media have grasped for examples of other elections that have caused trouble, many Americans are unaware that a remarkably large number of other elections have produced close results that nearly created political chaos.</p>

<p>The very first seriously contested presidential election, in 1800, was thrown into the House of Representatives after an Electoral College tie between Thomas Jefferson and Aaron Burr that resulted from a double-balloting anomaly in the Constitution. Jefferson was elected only after much maneuvering. The 1800 election, produced one positive result (aside from Jefferson's victory) insofar as it led to the 1804 enactment of the Twelfth Amendment, which eliminated double balloting.</p>

<p>The amendment retained, however, the curious procedure for election by the House of Representatives (voting by states) when no candidate receives a majority of the electoral vote. When no candidate received a majority of electors in 1824, the House elected John Quincy Adams even though Andrew Jackson had received a plurality of both the popular and electoral votes.</p>

<p>In four more elections during the next half century (1836, 1856, 1860), the shift of a relatively small number votes in a few states would have thrown the election into the House of Representatives. In six other elections (1828, 1840, 1844, 1848, 1864, and 1868), the shift of a small number of votes in a few states &mdash; fewer than 20,000 in the first four &mdash; would have resulted in the election of the other candidate. In most of these situations, the winning candidate would not have received a plurality of the popular vote. In three of these elections (1836,1844, and 1860), the final outcome was determined by the electoral votes of only one state, New York.</p>

<p>In 1876, the outcome of the election between Republican Rutherford B. Hayes and Democrat Samuel Tilden was in doubt for months as the result of the submission of double slates of electors in four states. In Florida, where both Republicans and Democrats alleged fraud, the governor certified Hayes electors, but a court ruled in favor of Tilden electors. In South Carolina, where fraud allegations also were rampant, Democrats submitted a slate of electors even though state officials had certified the Republican electors. In Louisiana, which had two governors,there were two competing canvassing boards and two conflicting sets of returns. And in Oregon, one Republican elector was challenged on a technicality. Congress eventually settled the dispute only by creating an electoral commission composed of eight Republicans and seven Democrats who voted on strict party lines, making Hayes the winner by the margin of one vote, even though he had lost the popular vote.</p>

<p>Only four years after the notorious election of 1876, the now largely forgotten election of 1880 nearly produced another crisis. Republican James A. Garfield's victory over Democrat Winfield Scott Hancock hinged on Garfield's capture of New York's 35 electors, which Garfield won by a margin of only 20,000 votes. Rumors of Republican vote fraud in New York were rampant during the days following the election, and the chairman of the Democratic National Committee and the leader of Tammany Hall seriously considered contesting the election.</p>

<p>Hancock did not concede for five days, and even then he publicly suggested that vote fraud had occurred in New York. Although Hancock believed for the remainder of the life that Garfield's victory was fraudulent, a book about the 1880 election has concluded that Hancock's "essential conservatism caused him to acquiesce in the results." In particular, Hancock probably feared that turmoil would be particularly injurious to the nation so soon after the turbulence of the 1876 election. Moreover, the reputation of the Republican Hayes Administration for honesty and efficiency also may have made a Democratic contest of the election impracticable.</p>

<p>Although no one knows whether the outcome of the 1880 was really the product of fraud, a Republican diplomat stationed in South Africa had written to Garfield during the summer of 1880 to propose that the G.O.P. import nine thousand voters into New York on election day from heavily Republican states that adjoin New York, and another six thousand from Canada. No reply from Garfield is known.</p>

<p>The 1880 election is also significant because it produced history's most narrow popular presidential vote, with Garfield winning by fewer than 8000 votes. The 1880 election therefore nearly became another election in which the winner of the electoral vote did not carry the popular vote.</p>

<p>Gilded Age presidential politics was a dicey affair. Like the election of 1880, the elections of both 1884 and 1888 hinged on the outcome in New York. In 1884, Grover Cleveland defeated James G. Blaine in New York by a margin of barely one thousand votes out of more than a million cast. Cleveland won the nation's popular vote by only 23,000 votes. In 1888, Cleveland was defeated by Benjamin Harrison, who carried New York by a margin of only one percent. Cleveland, however, won by more than one hundred thousand popular votes nationwide.</p>

<p>In the next three elections, the victor (Cleveland against Harrison in 1892 and William McKinley against William Jennings Bryan in 1896 and 1900) won by a comfortable margin of both popular and electoral votes. In each one of these elections, however, a shift of fewer than 75,000 votes in strategic states would have changed the election's outcome.</p>

<p>In 1916, another election hinged on a narrow vote in only one state. Woodrow Wilson, a Democrat, defeated Republican Charles Evans Hughes by only three thousand votes in California, where 13 electoral votes tipped the election to Wilson. Since Hughes carried most of the East, many newspapers declared Hughes the victor in early editions on the morning after the election and were as embarrassed as the television networks in the 2000 election when returns from the Midwest and West threw the election into doubt.</p>

<p>For another two days, the outcome was uncertain while votes were counted slowly in various closely contested states, especially in California, which the Democrats had at first conceded to the Republicans and in which the ballot format retarded tabulation efforts. Meanwhile, the national chairmen of both parties retained legal counsel in anticipation of litigation over the election, and the Democratic chairman wired state and county chairmen in various states to warn that Republicans were "desperate" and to urge that they personally guard the safety of ballot boxes. In words that could have been written during the past month, the American Review of Reviews in December 1916 observed that when "a presidential election is to be decided by the result in a single State, where the vote is so close as to be in doubt for a number of days, it is not surprising that there should be anxiety as well as suspense." Hughes did not concede until more than two weeks after the election. When Wilson finally received Hughes's telegram, he drily remarked that "it was a little moth-eaten...but quite legible."</p>

<p>Many factors may have contributed to Hughes's decision to refrain from contesting the election. First, Republicans may have feared that a challenge to California's votes would result in a Democratic challenge to the outcome in Minnesota, which Hughes had carried by only 396 votes; Wilson's victory in Minnesota would have enabled him to win the election without California's electoral votes. Moreover, Republicans do not appear to have had substantial evidence of irregularities in California. Hughes's decision to refrain from contesting the election also may have reflected ambivalence over whether he wanted to be president. Hughes was one of the very few persons ever to have been genuinely drafted to run for president. He made no effort to obtain the Republican nomination and resigned very reluctantly from the U.S. Supreme Court to accept it. Hughes correctly believed that the next president would have to lead the nation into war and that the incumbent party would suffer as the result of wartime strains. Hughes also may have been particularly reluctant to plunge the nation into an election crisis during a time when the nation was involved in international crises that clearly presaged war. Finally, Hughes may have felt that the result was fair insofar as Wilson won the popular vote by nearly 600,000 ballots, a margin of three percent.</p>

<p>After 1916, no election was close again until 1948. In 1924, however, the Electoral College created much anxiety during the months preceding the election. Although Republican Calvin Coolidge won by a modest landslide of popular and electoral votes, there were indications until late in the campaign that Robert M. LaFollette, running as a Progressive, might well carry enough Midwestern and Western states to throw the election into the House of Representatives. Speculation about various unsavory deals that might occur in the House abounded throughout the nation for several weeks. LaFollette, however, carried only his home state of Wisconsin.</p>

<p>In 1948, 1960, and 1968, the nation was narrowly spared having a winner who had lost the popular vote and/or the election decided by the House of Representatives. Moreover, the winner of the1968 election nearly lost the popular vote, and ballot ambiguities prevent any certain declaration about who won the popular vote in 1960.</p>

<p>In 1948, a shift of only about 24, 294 in three states (16,807 in Illinois, 8,933 in California, and 3,554 in Ohio) would have resulted in the election of Republican Thomas E. Dewey rather than Harry S Truman, even though Truman won the popular vote by more than two million. With third-party States' Rights candidate Strom Thurmond winning 39 electoral votes, the election would have been decided by the House of Representatives if Truman had lost two of these three states to Dewey.</p>

<p>In 1960, a shift of only about four thousand votes in Illinois and fewer than 25,000 votes in Texas would have enabled Richard M. Nixon to defeat John F. Kennedy. Since Harry F. Byrd received the electoral votes of fourteen unpledged electors from Mississippi and Alabama, plus the vote of a faithless elector from Oklahoma, the election would have been have thrown into the House if Kennedy had lost either Illinois or Texas together with any one of several closely-divided states that had enough electoral votes to deprive Kennedy of victory but not enough to enable Nixon to win.</p>

<p>Rumors of fraud in numerous states, particularly closely divided Illinois and Texas, encouraged Republicans to consider contesting the election. Since Nixon conceded to Kennedy on the day after the election and later encouraged the belief that he had stood aside only in order to prevent a constitutional crisis, many commentators in the wake of the 2000 pointed to Nixon's prompt concession as an example of good sportsmanship &mdash; often with the implication that Gore should be so magnanimously acquiescent. The myth that Nixon simply rolled over and played dead was recently shattered, however, by David Greenberg, a columnist for the online magazine Slate. Greenberg has demonstrated that Republicans investigated vote fraud charges, demanded recounts in eleven states, and filed lawsuits in Illinois, New Jersey, and Texas.</p>

<p>The popular vote was also very close, with Kennedy receiving an official plurality of only 112, 827 votes. Since there was some ambiguity about whether Alabama votes for Democratic electors were actually intended to be cast for Kennedy, whose name was not on the Alabama ballot, some scholars have suggested that Nixon actually won the popular vote. Since the intent of Alabama Democratic voters is impossible to discern, however, it remains impossible to say who actually won the popular vote.</p>

<p>In 1968, a shift of 53,024 votes from Nixon to Hubert H. Humphrey in New Jersey, Missouri, and New Hampshire would have thrown the election into the House of Representatives, since third-party candidate George C. Wallace won 45 electoral votes. A shift of slightly more than 100,000 votes in California would have had the same result. Moreover, the transfer of only a quarter of a million votes would have given Humphrey a plurality in the popular vote.</p>

<p>In 1976, a shift of only 5,559 votes in Ohio and 3,687 in Hawaii would have resulted in the election of Gerald R. Ford rather than James Earl Carter. And a shift of less than 12,000 votes in Ohio and Delaware would have produced a tie that would have sent the election to the House of Representatives. As in so many past elections, the outcome of the 1976 election hinged on the electoral vote of New York, which went for Carter by the relatively narrow margin of fewer than 300,000 votes. According to Electoral College experts Neal R. Peirce and Lawrence D. Longley, Republicans made allegations of voting irregularities in New York and demanded a recount on election night, but later decided not to proceed with an extended investigation. If an automatic recount had not confirmed Carter's victory in Ohio, Republicans might have investigated rumors of fraud and irregularities in Mississippi and Missouri. Republicans decided not to proceed with challenges at least in part because Carter's popular vote exceeded Ford's by a decisive 2.7 million.</p>

<p>Many of the closely divided elections have produced proposals for electoral reform. In particular, the 1968 and 1976 elections resulted in serious congressional consideration of abolition of the Electoral College. In 1979, a majority of senators  51-- actually voted to abolish the Electoral College, but this fell short of the two-thirds majority needed for a constitutional amendment.</p>

<p>Proposals for abolishing the Electoral College will almost certainly revive next year if, as seems likely, the winner of this year's election will have lost the popular vote. The expansion of popular democracy through the elimination of racial, gender, and economic disenfranchisement and the development of the "one person, one vote" principle in legislative apportionment suggests that Americans today will tolerate this anomaly far less gladly than did the Americans of 1824, 1876, and 1888. The actual occurrence of this anomaly would also provide the abolition movement with an impetus and an urgency that the movements following the 1968 and 1976 elections lacked.</p>

<p>But while abolition of the Electoral College would prevent the embarrassment of electing another president who had failed to win more popular votes than his or her opponent, it could actually exacerbate turmoil if the national vote were close. Rather than re-counting the votes of one or a few close states, the votes of all fifty states would need to be recounted. Imagine the Florida mess multiplied fifty-fold! Principles of federalism also favor retention of the Electoral College.</p>

<p>Accordingly, any serious consideration of electoral reform, with or without abolition of the Electoral College, needs also to consider various other reforms. In particular, both federal and state officials need to acknowledge that presidential elections affect critical national interests and therefore need to be regulated more carefully by federal authorities. The confusion over the format of ballots and counting procedures demonstrates that some type of more uniform system is needed for designing ballots and determining the procedure for counting them in a predictable and politically neutral manner. More standardized procedures for voter identification likewise are needed.</p>

<p>In addition to providing more unity to state procedure, any consideration of reform also needs to take account of congressional procedures. In particular, the creaky system of election by the House in the event of a deadlock needs careful scrutiny. When the Constitution was adopted, election by the House seemed more democratic because senators were not chosen by the people. The procedure which gives each state one vote also made more sense at a time when states' rights were more pronounced. Today it might make more sense to allow every member of Congress to vote to break the deadlock.</p>

<p>Reform proposals during the next year are also likely to include plans for providing a more refined procedure for determining the people's choice through run-off elections or a system used in some European countries that permits voters to list their choices in order of preference.</p>

<p>Ultimately, of course, no system can prevent close elections, provide for every legal contingency when a close election occurs, eliminate all fraud, or foreclose rancor arising from a closely contested election. The chaos arising out of the present election has amply demonstrated, however, that the present system invites uncertainty and turmoil. After the settlement of the present election, the nation will certainly turn its attention to efforts to devise more coherent and politically prudent procedures for presidential elections.</p>

<p><em><br />
William G. Ross teaches Constitutional Law and Constitutional History at Cumberland School of Law, Samford University, Birmingham, Alabama. He is a 1979 graduate of Harvard Law School.<br />
</em></p>

<p><strong>Suggested Citation</strong>: William G. Ross, Election Roulette: The Pistol Finally Fires, JURIST - Academic Commentary, Dec. 4, 2000, https://www.jurist.org/forum/2000/12/election-roulette-the-pistol-finally-fires.php</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The most complicated bit of governmental machinery which the modern world has to exhibit is that which is employed in the selection of the chief executive officer...for the United States...It is almost marvelous that any people should have preserved political...]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>80205</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2000-12-04 13:58:11]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2000-12-04 18:58:11]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[election-roulette-the-pistol-finally-fires]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="post_tag" nicename="affiliation-samford-university-school-of-law"><![CDATA[affiliation: Samford University School of Law]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="author-william-g-ross"><![CDATA[author: William G. Ross]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jurist_previous_post_status]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_pods_commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
					<item>
		<title>Bush v. Gore and the Prestige of the Supreme Court: A Self-inflicted Wound?</title>
		<link>https://www.jurist.org/commentary/2000/12/bush-v-gore-and-the-prestige-of-the-supreme-court/</link>
		<pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2000 19:05:03 +0000</pubDate>
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[jdl]]></dc:creator>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://jurist.org/forum/2000/12/bush-v-gore-and-the-prestige-of-the-supreme-court.php</guid>
		<description></description>
		<content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>The Court's authority &mdash; possessed of neither the purse nor the sword &mdash; ultimately rests on sustained public confidence in its moral sanction. Such feeling must be nourished by the Court's complete detachment, in fact and appearance, from political entanglements and by abstention from injecting itself into the clash of political forces in political settlements.</blockquote>
 Felix Frankfurter, dissenting in Baker v. Carr, 1962.

<p>Justice Frankfurter's eloquent warning about the Supreme Court's need to remain detached from political entanglements was echoed yesterday by Justice Stephen Breyer in his dissent in Bush v. Gore. Breyer aptly warned that "the appearance of a split decision runs the risk of undermining the public's confidence in the Court itself. That confidence is a public treasure." Borrowing language that Charles Evans Hughes used to describe the Court's disastrous Dred Scott decision, Breyer expressed fear that the Court risked "a self-inflicted wound &mdash; a wound that may harm not just the Court, but the Nation."</p>

<p>The danger that the Court's decision in Bush will be viewed as partisan is particularly acute because all five "conservative" members opposed Gore's plea for additional vote recounts, while all four "liberal" members took a contrary position. Each of the Justices moreover favored a position on federalism that is ostensibly contrary to his or her usual position. The five Justices who usually favor states' rights displayed the least deference to the Florida Supreme Court's decision, while the four Justices who normally support stronger federal power advocated a higher level of deference to the Florida court. The appearance of partisan division is only partly mitigated by the willingness of Justices Souter and Breyer to agree with the conservative majority that "there are constitutional problems with the recount ordered by Florida that demand a remedy."</p>

<p>Of course, the appearance of partisanship is not the same as the reality of partisanship. Indeed, a Justice who ruled against his opinion of the law in order to avoid the appearance of partisanship would be as miscreant as a Justice who based his ruling on his partisan preferences. As the Democratic Chief Justice of Arizona observed in a 1917 decision in which the Supreme Court of Arizona ruled in favor of a Democratic gubernatorial candidate in an election dispute that had dragged on for more than a year, the court could not allow "the political affiliations of its members" to influence its decision even though to some critics its judgment "may appear not to be impartial unless it be against the [Democratic] contestant or unfair to him."</p>

<p>Critics of the Court decision contend that the Court's need to decide the Bush case was less compelling than it has been in cases in which the other branches of the state or federal governments had failed to properly redress wrongs. As Justice Breyer observed, "the Court is not acting to vindicate a fundamental constitutional principle, such as the need to protect a basic human liberty." Breyer declared that "no preeminent legal concern, or practical concern related to legal questions, required this Court to hear this case, let alone to issue a stay that stopped Florida's recount process in its tracks." In contrast, Chief Justice Rehnquist contended in his concurring opinion that a disputed presidential election raised issues of compelling national importance that were appropriate for the Court to decide.</p>

<p>Although Breyer acknowledged that "the selection of the President is of fundamental national importance," he declared that this "importance is political, not legal. And this Court should resist the temptation unnecessarily to resolve tangential legal disputes, where doing so threatens to determine the outcome of the election."</p>

<p>Breyer compared the Court's intervention in the 2000 election with the membership of five U.S. Supreme Court Justices in the congressionally-created Electoral Commission that in 1877 settled the disputed election of 1876. Breyer contended that the participation of the five Justices "did not lend that process legitimacy," but "[r]ather, it simply embroiled Members of the Court in partisan conflict, thereby undermining respect for the judicial process."</p>

<p>Breyer recalled that Justice Joseph P. Bradley, a Republican Justice who cast the decisive vote in favor of the Republican candidate Rutherford B. Hayes, "immediately became the subject of vociferous attacks" in which he was accused of accepting bribes and succumbing to pressure from railroad interests and Republican politicians. Breyer did not mention that Bradley received so many threatening communications that the government placed his house under guard.</p>

<p>In his book From Confederation to Nation: The American Constitution, 1835-1877, Bernard Schwartz acknowledged that the "charge against Bradley's integrity severely tarnished his remaining career" and that the "spectacle of the justices casting their votes on partisan lines cannot but have had a deleterious effect upon the Court's reputation." Schwartz indicated, however, that the Court's participation in the dispute was worth the price. In contrast to Breyer's contention that the participation of the five Justices in the settlement of the election failed to legitimize the process, Schwartz plausibly argued that "it is doubtful that the Electoral Commission could ever had been approved &mdash; much less had its decision accepted by the country" if the five Justices had not served as members of the Commission.</p>

<p>Although criticism of Bradley and the other justices was widespread and intense, the episode produced no significant or sustained effort to curb the Court's power. Moreover, the Court's prestige does not appear to have suffered for long, and the episode did not prevent the Court from embarking on a new era of dubious activism during the next few years, when it began to craft doctrines that limited the powers of state and federal authorities to enact economic regulatory legislation and to prevent racial discrimination. When the Court came under prolonged attack during the period between 1890 and 1937 for its hostility toward economic regulatory legislation, the role of the five Justices in the 1876 election was virtually ignored even by ferocious critics of the Court who copiously attacked the Court and various Justices for alleged misdeeds that long predated 1876.</p>

<p>Additionally, Breyer's analogy to the election of 1876 is not altogether apt because the Justices who sat on the Electoral Commission were acting extra-judicially and were exercising a quasi-political function. The tenacious public deference toward the Supreme Court is a respect for the Court as an institution and for the rule of law and it does not extend to the non-judicial activities of the Justices. This is why one reason why Chief Justice Warren was so reluctant to chair the commission that investigated the John F. Kennedy assassination, and why Justices generally abjure extra-judicial activities. Although the participation of the five Justices in the Electoral Commission did not deter the Court from soon embarking on a new era of judicial activism, it discouraged Justices from undertaking other public functions and has served as an object lesson down to the present day.</p>

<p>The deleterious impact of the 1876 election dispute on the Court was not that it damaged its prestige but rather that the end of Reconstruction, to which Republicans agreed in return for Democratic acquiescence to Hayes's election, encouraged some Justices &mdash; including Bradley &mdash; to begin dismantling civil rights protections for African-Americans.</p>

<p>Like Breyer, Justice Stevens warned in dissent in Bush that the Court's decision could adversely affect judicial prestige, but he ostensibly confined his remarks to the decision's impact upon state courts.</p>

<p>Stevens charged that the Court had endorsed Bush's tacit "lack of confidence in the impartiality and capacity of the state judges who would make the critical decisions if the vote count were to proceed." He expressed fear that "[t]he endorsement of that position by the majority of this Court can only lend credence to the most cynical appraisal of the work of judges throughout the land." Declaring that "the true background of the rule of law" is "confidence in the men and women who administer the judicial system," Stevens declared that while "we may never know with complete certainty the identity of the winner of this year's Presidential election, the identity of the loser is perfectly clear. It is the Nation's confidence in the judge as an impartial guardian of the rule of law."</p>

<p>Stevens' fear is misplaced. There is little likelihood that many members of the public will understand the Court's complex opinion well enough to interpret it as lacking confidence in the state judiciary. And those who understand the opinion well enough to draw this conclusion are well able to form an independent opinion about the fairness of state judges. Even if the Court's opinion did adversely affect public perception of the Florida courts, the opinion would not necessarily tarnish public respect for other state courts.</p>

<p>Stevens' remarks about the impact of the decision on public confidence in the state judiciary would have greater resonance if applied to public confidence in the Supreme Court. The greatest danger is that, by spending some of its precious goodwill &mdash; Breyer's "public treasure" &mdash; the Court will enjoy less public support in future years when it adjudicates controversial public issues that more clearly lie within its jurisdiction and about which it has a more compelling need to make a decision.</p>

<p>This danger is subtle and is part of the very delicate balance between public opinion and judicial power that has enabled the Court to command obedience even when its decisions have been controversial. The threat is not immediate. Since the Court's intervention in the election is an isolated incident rather than part of any on-going controversy, the Court's decision &mdash; as Justice Breyer acknowledged in his dissent &mdash; is not likely to precipitate any movement to curtail the Court's powers. Any intense animosity arising out the decision may fade as quickly as did the rancor that was directed against the Court in 1877.</p>

<p>Critics of the Court's decision are more likely to direct their wrath against individual Justices rather than against the Court as an institution. Gore supporters who revile the Court's decision are mostly liberals who are likely to continue to revere the Court for its historic services to the cause of civil liberties and to maintain their faith in the Court's role as the ultimate guardian of justice. The abiding respect of liberals for the Court was demonstrated during this year's presidential campaign, when the Court emerged as a significant election issue for the first time since 1968. Although liberals castigated the Court for its many recent five-to-four conservative decisions, their remedy was not to curb the Court's powers but rather to elect a president who would appoint liberals to the Court. Since many liberals have alleged for years that the conservative Justices have politicized the Court, the Justices who ruled in favor of Bush had little goodwill to lose among liberals.</p>

<p>Despite the real threats to the Court's prestige, the Bush v. Gore decision may ultimately help to inspire greater confidence in the Court among many Americans who may have despaired of the ability of the Florida courts or legislature, or the U.S. Congress, to resolve what had rapidly become a constitutional crisis. Although critics of the Court's decision make a good argument that other political agencies were at least as well able to ensure a lawful and peaceful transfer of presidential power, the immense public respect that the Court commands almost certainly will help to confer greater legitimacy on the outcome on the election than if other public entities had resolved the constitutional issues. The paradox is that the Court's adjudication of the controversy may have caused the Court to lose some of its own legitimacy.</p>

<p>Meanwhile, any Justices who are wrongly accused of partisanship should take solace in Justice Bradley's equanimity in responding to the widespread vituperation that he suffered for casting the vote that threw the 1876 election to Hayes: "So far as I am capable of judging my own motives, I did not allow political, that is, party, considerations to have any weight whatsoever in forming my conclusion. I know it is difficult for men of the world to believe this, but I know it, and that is enough for me."</p>

<p><em><br />
William G. Ross teaches Constitutional Law and Constitutional History at Cumberland School of Law, Samford University, Birmingham, Alabama. He is a 1979 graduate of Harvard Law School.<br />
</em></p>

<p><strong>Suggested Citation</strong>: William G. Ross, Bush v. Gore and the Prestige of the Supreme Court: A Self-inflicted Wound?, JURIST - Academic Commentary, Dec. 13, 2000, https://www.jurist.org/forum/2000/12/bush_v_gore_and_the_prestige_of_the_supreme_court.php.</p>]]></content:encoded>
		<excerpt:encoded><![CDATA[The Court's authority &mdash; possessed of neither the purse nor the sword &mdash; ultimately rests on sustained public confidence in its moral sanction. Such feeling must be nourished by the Court's complete detachment, in fact and appearance, from political entanglements...]]></excerpt:encoded>
		<wp:post_id>80206</wp:post_id>
		<wp:post_date><![CDATA[2000-12-13 14:05:03]]></wp:post_date>
		<wp:post_date_gmt><![CDATA[2000-12-13 19:05:03]]></wp:post_date_gmt>
		<wp:comment_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:comment_status>
		<wp:ping_status><![CDATA[closed]]></wp:ping_status>
		<wp:post_name><![CDATA[bush-v-gore-and-the-prestige-of-the-supreme-court]]></wp:post_name>
		<wp:status><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:status>
		<wp:post_parent>0</wp:post_parent>
		<wp:menu_order>0</wp:menu_order>
		<wp:post_type><![CDATA[post]]></wp:post_type>
		<wp:post_password><![CDATA[]]></wp:post_password>
		<wp:is_sticky>0</wp:is_sticky>
										<category domain="post_tag" nicename="affiliation-samford-university-school-of-law"><![CDATA[affiliation: Samford University School of Law]]></category>
		<category domain="post_tag" nicename="author-william-g-ross"><![CDATA[author: William G. Ross]]></category>
		<category domain="category" nicename="uncategorized"><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
						<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_jurist_previous_post_status]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[publish]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[_pods_commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							<wp:postmeta>
		<wp:meta_key><![CDATA[commentary_type]]></wp:meta_key>
		<wp:meta_value><![CDATA[Forum]]></wp:meta_value>
		</wp:postmeta>
							</item>
				</channel>
</rss>
	
<!--
Performance optimized by W3 Total Cache. Learn more: https://www.boldgrid.com/w3-total-cache/

Page Caching using disk: enhanced{w3tc_pagecache_reject_reason}
Database Caching using disk (Request-wide wp-admin)

Served from: www.jurist.org @ 2020-05-23 17:52:23 by W3 Total Cache
-->